HUMAN 
RIGHTS 
WATCH 
THEY CAM E TO KILL 
ESCALATING ATROCITIES 
IN THE CENTRALAFRICAN REPUBLIC 
Since September 2013, predominantly Ciiristian militias 
known as the anti-balaka and largely Muslim ex-Seleka 
forces, which ousted the previous government in March, 
have committed brutal sectarian violence against civilians 
in Ouham province in northern CentralAfrican Republic. 
"They Came to Kill," based on field research in October 
and November, describes how anti-balaka militias, 
avenging ex-Seleka abuses, carried out coordinated 
attacks in September against Muslim communities 
and ex-Seleka outposts near Bossangoa, the Ouham 
provincial capital. Anti-balaka forces, which comprise 
village-level self-defense formations and soldiers loyal to 
the previous government, killed several hundred Muslims 
residents, burned their homes, and stole their cattle. 
Ex-Seleka forces, a coalition of rebel groups, retaliated 
against Christian civilians, killing many people and 
setting fire to their homes. Senior ex-Seleka commanders 
in Bossangoa appear to have condoned these attacks. 
The incidents documented in this report reflect only 
a fraction ofthe abuses committed against both 
Christians and Muslims since the Seleka, as they were 
then known, took power. 
Human Rights Watch calls on the country's interim 
government to rein in the ex-Seleka, who are nominally 
part ofthe armed forces; protect all civilians from 
attack; and facilitate the delivery of urgently needed 
humanitarian aid. Concerned countries should 
immediately bolsterthe current African Union 
peacekeeping force in the Central African Republic and 
support French efforts to respond robustly to the fighting 
to protect the civilian population from further abuses and 
prevent greater humanitarian catastrophe. 
^^ST 
'<-2 

%. 
' 4 
V 
^■^■'- 
...    I 
^fe 
a?: 
«k» 
/ 
^ 
x^ 
# 
^^ 
I 
\ 
% 
A 
'K 
.f \,' 
-J 
'■Hi 
fiâl 
CAM E TO KILL 
^  ESCALATING ATROCITIES 
^N THE CENTRALAFRICAN REPUBLIC 
Weapons confiscated from anti-balaka and ex-Seleka 
Union peacekeepers in tiie town of Bossangoa. Decen 
© 2013 IVlarcus Bleasdale/VII for Human Rigiits Watc 


Copyright© 2013 Human Rights Watch 
All rights reserved. 
Printed in the United States ofAmerica 
ISBN: 978-1-62313-0886 
Cover design by Fruitmachine 
Human Rights Watch is dedicated to protectingthe human rights of people around the 
world. We stand with victims and activists to prevent discrimination, to uphold political 
freedom, to protect people from inhumane conduct in wartime, and to bring offenders 
to justice. We investigate and expose human rights violations and hold abusers 
accountable. We challenge governments and those who hold powerto end abusive 
practices and respect international human rights law. We enlist the public and the 
international community to support the cause of human rights for all. 
Human Rights Watch is an international organization with staffln morethan 40 
countries, and offices in Amsterdam, Beirut, Berlin, Brussels, Chicago, Geneva, Goma, 
Johannesburg, London, Los Angeles, Moscow, Nairobi, New York, Paris, San Francisco, 
Tokyo, Toronto, Tunis, Washington DC, and Zurich. 
For more information, please visit our website: http://www.hrw.org 
Acknowledgments 
This report was written by Peter Bouckaert, emergencies director at Human Rights 
Watch, based on research he conducted during two missions: in Octoberand 
Novemberwith Philippe Bolopion, UN director, and anotherin early December 
2013. Photographer Marcus Bleasdale joined both research trips, josh Lyons, satellite 
imagery analyst in the emergencies division, provided satellite imagery ofthe Central 
African Republic. 
The report was reviewed by Rona Peligal, deputy director ofthe Africa division; Philippe 
Bolopion; Lewis Mudge, researcher, Africa division; jean-Marie Fardeau, France 
director; Bede Sheppard, deputy director, children's rights division; Liesl Gerntholtz, 
executive director, women's rights division; James Ross, legal and policy director; and 
Babatunde Olugboji, deputy program director. Katya Salmi, fellow in the Africa division, 
and Joyce Bukuru, associate in the Africa division, provided editorial assistance. 
Grace Choi, publications director; Veronica Matushaj, documentary video and photo 
director; Ivy Shen, multimedia officer; and Fitzroy Hepkins, administrative manager, 
prepared the report for publication. 
Human Rights Watch expresses its gratitude to the many victims and witnesses and 
others who provided personal accounts, evidence, and information forthis report. 
THEY CAM E TO KILL 
Escalating Atrocities in tine CentralAfrican Republic 
Acknowledgments. 
Summary. 
Methodology. 
Recommendations...................................................................................................................................................8 
To the Transitional Government ofthe Central African Republic............................................................................8 
To ex-Seleka and anti-balaka forces.....................................................................................................................8 
To the United Nations Security Council................................................................................................................8 
To the African Union Peace and Security Council..................................................................................................8 
To the Prosecutor ofthe International Criminal Court (ICC)...................................................................................8 
To France, the United Kingdom, the European Union, the United States, and Other Concerned Governments.......8 
I. Background........................................................................................................................................................11 
II. Anti-Balaka Abuses against Muslim Communities near Bossangoa.....................................................................17 
Zéré..................................................................................................................................................................18 
Gbakora/Bandorok............................................................................................................................................22 
Ouham-Bac.......................................................................................................................................................24 
Bodora..............................................................................................................................................................24 
Votovo..............................................................................................................................................................24 
Bossangoa........................................................................................................................................................25 
Attacks on Mbororo Cattle Camps......................................................................................................................26 
III. Ex-Seleka Abuses Against Christians.................................................................................................................29 
Attacks Inside Bossangoa..................................................................................................................................30 
Attacks Outside Bossangoa...............................................................................................................................32 
IV. Humanitarian Catastrophe: "Livingand Dying Like Animals".............................................................................36 
The Displacement Crisis....................................................................................................................................36 
The Health Crisis...............................................................................................................................................40 
The Education Crisis..........................................................................................................................................42 
2 THEY CAM E TO KILL 
THEYCAMET0KILL3 

People displaced by the fighting between ex-Seleka and anti-balaka 
forces find shelter in an old factory on the grounds ofthe Catholic 
church in Bossangoa. November 2, 2013. 
© 2013 Marcus Bleasdale/VII for Human Rights Watch 
SUMMARY 
^ 
fi 


^ 
^. 
\ 
N 
^. 
* 
S 
* 
y 
I. '^a 
V.V. /■ 

> 
V 
r 
<-^, 
yr 
< jr      r 
1 
-£ 
#.. 
.^ 
t 
-^ 
^•«^i 
LJ 
ß 
^ 
fe 
In September 2013, the CentralAfrican Republic's 
human rights and humanitarian situation took a 
sharp turn for the worse. After months of brutality 
bythe predominantly Muslim Seleka ("alliance") 
forces, which had overthrown the government 
of President François Bozizé in March, Christian 
militias known as the anti-balaka ("anti-machete") 
began to organize counterattacks. The anti-balaka, 
which began as local self-defense groups under 
Bozizé, have targeted Muslim communities and 
committed numerous abuses. 
Anti-balaka atrocities have been particularly 
widespread in Ouham province, north ofthe 
national capital, Bangui. On September 6, anti- 
balaka fighters launched coordinated attacks 
on Muslim communities and isolated ex-Seleka 
outposts in market towns surrounding the 
provincial capital, Bossangoa. Anti-balaka forces 
killed several hundred Muslims residents, burned 
their homes, and stole or killed their cattle, a 
precious source of income and wealth. 
Many ofthe attacks involved shocking brutality: 
one Muslim woman, a nomadic cattle herder, 
told Human Rights Watch that she was forced to 
watch as anti-balaka fighters cut the throats of her 
3-year-old son, two other boys ages 10 and 14, 
and an adult relative—all the Muslim males in the 
cattle camp. A 55-year-old man tearfully described 
escaping from anti-balaka attackers, only to watch 
in horror from a hiding place as they proceeded 
to cut the throats of his two wives, his 10 children 
and a grandchild, as well as other Muslim civilians 
they had captured. Some ofthe survivors reported 
hearing anti-balaka fighters say they intended to 
kill "all the Muslims." 
4 THEY CAM E TO KILL 
THEYCAMETO KILLS 


METHODOLOGY 
The ex-Seleka forces in Ouham province, suffering 
significant losses from the anti-balaka attacks, 
retreated to Bossangoa. There, they wreaked 
revenge on Christian residents, killing many and 
setting fire to their homes. Michel Djotodia, the 
Seleka leader who in August was officially sworn 
in as interim president until the 2015 elections, 
announced in September that the Seleka were 
being dissolved. However, the now "ex-Seleka" 
fighters continue to operate across the country, 
continuing their string of abuse. 
Former Seleka fighters conducted frequent 
attacks against farmers working in their fields. 
Such killings appearto have had the backing of 
senior ex-Seleka commanders in Bossangoa. On 
November 18, the current ex-Seleka commander 
of Bossangoa, Colonel Saleh, in the presence 
of a dozen of his officers, including his then- 
superior. General Yaya (who has since died in 
the December5 fighting in Bangui) ordered them 
to drown seven farmers who were wrongfully 
accused of being anti-balaka militia. The farmers 
were bound and thrown alive into the Ouham 
River; three survived. 
Both sides have burned down dozens of villages in 
the province. Entire stretches of land have simply 
been abandoned because of fear of ex-Seleka 
attacks, and it is possible to drive for hours around 
Bossangoa without seeing a single resident in their 
home. Some 40,000 displaced Christians sought 
the safety of the Catholic church in Bossangoa, 
while 4,000 displaced Muslims were living in 
the opposite end of town, a bitter symbol ofthe 
ruptured communal ties in the country. 
In early December, this fragmentation came to a 
head. Anti-balaka militias chased ex-Seleka forces 
from much of Bossangoa, and slaughtered at least 
11 Muslim civilians in the Muslim Boro quarter of 
the city. The next morning, ex-Seleka commander 
Colonel Saleh took his regrouped fighters to the 
outskirts ofthe Catholic church, where his men 
then fired several rocket-propelled grenades into 
the crowded camp and repeatedly threatened to 
attack it unless the anti-balaka left Bossangoa. 
Hoping to avoid a massacre, African peacekeepers 
negotiated an end to the crisis, persuaded 
the anti-balaka to stand down, and possibly 
prevented a bloodbath. 
The latest gruesome killings in Bossangoa present 
only one small segment of a much broader tragedy 
that has been unfolding in the Central African 
Republic. With between 400 to 500 dead in 
similarly brutal clashes and massacres in early 
December in Bangui, little doubt remains that 
the CentralAfrican Republic is engulfed in ever- 
widening sectarian bloodshed. France has taken 
note of how critical the situation has become and 
has sent hundreds of additional French troops to 
the country to assist the African peacekeeping 
force in providing protection to civilians, but it 
is still struggling to find support for a broader 
international stabilization force forthe country 
under United Nations command. 
Withoutsome measure of security, it will be 
difficult to address the enormous humanitarian 
catastrophe in the CentralAfrican Republic. In a 
deeply impoverished country of fewer than five 
million people, some 450,000 have been forced 
to flee their homes, including 170,000 in Ouham 
province alone. At least 70,000 have become 
refugees in neighboring Democratic Republic of 
the Congo, Cameroon, and other countries. 
Humanitarian relief workers in northern Central 
African Republic have found it difficultto provide 
assistance, particularly emergency medical aid, 
as violence - some targeting the aid workers 
themselves - impedes an effective response 
to the crisis. In September, ex-Seleka fighters 
systematically looted health centers around 
Bossangoa, denying the population access to 
meaningful medical care. Deaths from malaria 
and other diseases compound the death toll. In 
northern CentralAfrican Republic, blackboards in 
abandoned schools often still display the date in 
March when children were last in class. 
This report examines the events in Bossangoa 
town and Ouham province from September 
through early December 2013, leading up to 
the latest round of bloodshed. A Human Rights 
Watch research team spent two weeks in the 
Central African Republic in early November, and 
an additional two weeks in early December, 
investigating the deadly and brutal sectarian 
violence perpetrated by both ex-Seleka and anti- 
balaka forces. Human Rights Watch documented 
more than 120 killings by the anti-balaka and at 
least 37 killings by the ex-Seleka in and around 
Bossangoa. Atrocities by both sides continue 
to escalate, and are likely to spin further out of 
control without more robust international action. 
This report is based on field research conducted in the 
Central African Republic during two two-week missions 
in October and November and early December 2013 by 
a Human Rights Watch research team, which included 
an independent photographer and videographer. The 
research team conducted interviews in the capital, 
Bangui; Bossangoa, the provincial capital of Ouham; 
and in towns and villages around Bossangoa, including 
Ndjo, Zéré, Wikamo, and Ouham-Bac. 
Human Rights Watch interviewed more than 60 
witnesses and survivors of abuses by both ex-Seleka 
and anti-balaka fighters. Interviews were conducted 
in French, Sango, or Arabic with the assistance of 
interpreters. None ofthe individuals interviewed forthis 
report were paid or given other incentives to provide 
information. 
Human Rights Watch also interviewed Christian and 
Muslim religious leaders, as well as leaders ofthe anti- 
balaka and ex-Seleka militias, officials ofthe Economic 
Community of Central African States' Multinational 
Force of Central Africa (FOMAC), United Nations 
officials, diplomats, humanitarian workers, and Interim 
President Michel Djotodia. 
Because ofthe possibility of reprisal, the names of 
some witnesses, family members, and friends of victims 
who spoke to Human Rights Watch have been withheld 
from this report. 
6THEYCAMET0KILL 
THEYCAMETO KILL7 


RECOMMENDATIONS 
TO THE TRANSITIONAL GOVERNMENT 
OFTHE CENTRALAFRICAN REPUBLIC 
•     Provide unambiguous and public orders to 
securityforces prohibiting attacks on civilians, 
the destruction or looting of civilian property, and 
the killing or mistreatment of anyone in custody, 
including captured alleged anti-balaka fighters or 
supporters. 
•     Disarm ex-Seleka fighters who have been relieved 
oftheir duties under President Djotodia's 
September dissolution ofthe group, and take 
action againstthose continuing to operate 
unlawfully. Provide the list of commanders acting 
underthe provisional government's authority. 
•     Provide full cooperation to the French and African 
Union troops deployed under UN Security Council 
Resolution 2127 to protect civilians and signal 
support for a UN peacekeeping mission. 
•     Facilitate access by humanitarian agencies 
to provide food, medicine, shelter, and other 
essentials to displaced and at-risk populations. 
•     Protect all civilians vulnerable to attacks by ex- 
Seleka and anti-balaka forces. 
•     Aft:er a vetting process to exclude individuals 
responsible for human rights abuses, reinstate 
members ofthe police, gendarmerie, and regular 
army after providing appropriate human rights 
training. Deny government positions to ex-Seleka 
fighters found responsible for serious human 
rights abuses. 
•     Investigate and prosecute, in accordance with 
international fair trial standards, all persons 
against whom there is evidence of criminal 
responsibility for grave crimes, including those 
liable under command responsibility, for their 
failure to prevent or prosecute crimes. 
•     Take all necessary and appropriate steps to 
permit school-age children to return to school, 
and rebuild and repair schools affected bythe 
violence. 
TO EX-SELEKA AND ANTI-BALAKA FORCES 
•     Cease immediately all attacks on civilians and 
civilian properties or structures, including medical 
centers and schools. 
•     Surrender weapons to the appropriate authorities. 
•     Cease all recruitment and use of children as 
soldiers. 
•     Allow humanitarian agencies to provide assistance 
to civilians throughoutthe country. 
TO THE UNITED NATIONS SECURITY 
COUNCIL 
•     Authorize the deployment ofa multi-dimensional 
UN peacekeeping mission under ChapterVll ofthe 
UN Charter with a robust mandate and the means 
to protect civilians, promote human rights, and 
create an environment conducive to the delivery of 
humanitarian aid. 
•     Impose an asset freeze and a travel ban on 
individuals credibly implicated in serious human 
rights abuses. 
•     If requested by the UN secretary-general, authorize 
the redeployment, on an emergency basis, of troops 
and assets from neighboring UN peacekeeping 
missions to protect the civilians most at risk. 
TO THE AFRICAN UNION PEACE AND 
SECURITYCOUNCIL 
•     Ensure that the African-led International Support 
Mission in the CentralAfrican Republic (MISCA) has 
the necessary logistical and financial support to 
protect all civilian populations. 
•     Consider troop deployment from other African Union 
member states to bolster MlSCA's capacity. 
•     Disarm the anti-balaka and ex-Seleka forces. 
•     Protect vulnerable civilians in towns and rural areas. 
•     Create a hotline that would enable civilians to report 
human rights abuses. 
TO THE PROSECUTOR OFTHE 
INTERNATIONAL CRIMINAL COURT (ICC) 
•     Continue to actively monitor developments 
in the Central African Republic to determine 
whether crimes within the ICC's jurisdiction are 
being committed. 
•     Remind all parties ofthe ICC's jurisdiction 
and, as appropriate, issue public statements 
assessing the gravity ofthe crimes committed in 
the CentralAfrican Republic. 
TO FRANCE, THE UNITED KINGDOM, THE 
EUROPEAN UNION, THE UNITED STATES, 
AND OTHER CONCERNED GOVERNMENTS 
•     Support the creation ofa UN peacekeeping mission 
under ChapterVll ofthe UN Charter with a robust 
mandate and the means to protect civilians, 
promote human rights, and create an environment 
conducive to the delivery of humanitarian aid. 
•     Immediately provide the necessary financial, 
logistical, and technical support to African Union 
peacekeepers, including airlift capacity and 
additional security, medical, and communications 
equipment. 
•     Increase support for humanitarian assistance to aid 
populations at risk, including displaced persons 
and refugees. 
•     Support programs that protect, demobilize, and 
rehabilitate child soldiers, and assist in the repair 
and rebuilding of schools. 
•     Assist national authorities in their efforts to restore 
the rule oflaw. 
8 THEY CAM E TO KILL 
THEYCAMETO KILL9 


Ex-Seleka fighters at a checkpoint on the road out of Bossangoa. They regularly 
rob local residents who have to cross the checkpoint to return to town after 
searching for food in the countryside. November 4, 2013. 
© 2013 Marcus Bleasdale/VII for Human Rights Watch 
.BACKGROUND 
W' 
-n(t 
I- 
ï: 

^ 
% 
J^ 
N 
V 
f 
% 
% 
Gi. 
A 
n; 
m 
r 
% 
I 
k 

WJS 
-m 
i9a 
I 
n 
^ 
On December 10, 2012, the Seleka, an alliance of 
predominantly Muslim rebel groups from the Central 
African Republic's marginalized northeast, began a 
military campaign against the government of President 
François Bozizé.^ On March 24, 2013, Seleka rebels 
took control of Bangui, the capital, and ousted Bozizé. 
Michel Djotodia, one ofthe Seleka leaders, suspended 
the constitution, and installed himself as interim 
president—a role to which he was subsequently 
appointed bythe transitional government. New national 
elections are scheduled for early 2015. 
The Seleka asserted that they would bring peace and 
security to the confiict-ridden country, but under Seleka 
rule, the Central African Republic has been wracked by 
widespread violence and human rights abuses. Seleka 
forces have looted communities across the country, 
killed numerous people, raped countless women and 
girls, and burned entire villages to the ground.^ The 
exact number is unknown, and many parts ofthe Central 
African Republic, because ofthe ongoingviolence and 
poor road conditions, are difficult to reach. 
President Djotodia dissolved the Seleka in September 
2013, but many now "ex-Seleka" fighters continue 
to operate across the country.^ Nominally integrated 
into the national army, ex-Seleka continue to exert 
their powerthrough violence in much ofthe country, 
terrorizing local populations. They have increasingly 
been opposed by predominantly Christian militias known 
as anti-balaka ("anti-machete" in Sango), which in 
September began to strike back at the ex-Seleka forces. 
1  "Seleka" means "alliance" in Sango, the national language ofthe 
CentralAfrican Republic. 
2  Human Rights Watch, I Can StillSmellthe Dead: The Forgotten 
Human Rights Crisis in the CentralAfrican Republic, https://www.hrw. 
org/reports/2013/09/18/i-can-still-smell-dead. 
3 "Central African Republic: Horrific Abuses by New Rulers. 
Ex-Rebel Coalition Should Restore Security, Provide Aid," Human 
Rights Watch news release, September 28, 2013, http://www.hrw.org/ 
news/2013/09/18/central-african-republic-horrific-abuses-new-rulers. 
The Seleka now call themselves "ex-Seleka," which is how the group is 
referred to in this report. 
lOTHEYCAMETOKILL 
THEYCAMETO KILL 11 


An anti-balaka fighter stands in a stream nearthe trading center of Ndjo, which displaced residents cross 
daily to reach their shelters in the bush. Most ofthe town's 14,000 residents fled to these remote areas, 
which lack clean water and medicine. The village's health center was raided in September 2013, and all 
its medical supplies were looted. November 5, 2013. 
© 2013 Marcus Bleasdale/VII for Human Rights Watch 
The anti-balaka originally presented themselves as local 
self-defense groups, but more and more have targeted enfire 
Muslim communities, claiming to be retaliating for ex-Seleka 
abuses. Anti-balaka militias, which do not have a strong 
centralized command structure, are currently strongest in 
northwest Central African Republic, but on December 5 
they staged large-scale attacks on Bangui and Bossangoa. 
These groups contain some heavily armed former soldiers 
who had defected from the armed forces under Bozizé, the 
Forces Armées Centrafricaines (FACA), including elements of 
Bozizé's Presidential Guard, commonly known (in English) 
as the Red Berets. 
The country's population of nearly five million is about 80 
percent Christian. Muslims constitute about 15 percent 
ofthe population, and are mostly concentrated in the far 
northeast ofthe country. Elsewhere, Muslims form an 
even smaller percentage ofthe population, and are often 
associated with commerce in the trading centers and 
nomadic cattle herding. 
Amongthe Muslims are ethnic Peuhl, many of whom engage 
in the cattle trade. The Mbororo are a subgroup ofthe Peuhl 
and are Muslim nomads who can be found in many west 
and central African countries. They continue to practice 
pastoral nomadism, their traditional way of life, moving with 
large herds of livestock from grazing area to grazing area, 
even though much ofthe livestock is now oft:en owned by 
Muslim traders rather than the Mbororo guarding them. 
The Mbororos' pastoral nomadism often brings them into 
confiict with sedentary (and predominantly Christian Gbaya) 
farmers, whose crops are sometimes eaten by the migrating 
livestock. The distinctive ethnic features and dress ofthe 
Mbororo make them easy to identify, and Mbororo nomads 
and Gbaya sedentary farmers are often in confiict, each 
having biased views ofthe other group. 
Sango and French are the official languages ofthe Central 
African Republic. Many Seleka fiighters are Muslim and 
speakArabic, and they mostly come from the country's 
northeast, in an area located between Chad and Sudan's 
Darfur region. 
^ 
■/*r' 
^: 
&: 
f^ 
i 
<%- 
ÄÄ' 
>-: 
T*. 
Jf 
f'<i   • . 
- .     •* 
'1 

■Jß- 
ï:^ . 
1*«tir      r- 
>sr=*^ 
^€ 
â r 
.^ 
< -■    .; -' -i-   ^ 
^i&*^ 
? 

•^*- 
é" 
€H 

"^i^^£^üi?; 
12THEYCAMET0KILL 
THEYCAMETO KILL 13 


MAP OF FEATURED 
REPORT LOCATIONS 
Human Rights Watch interviewed more than 60 witnesses 
and survivors of abuses by both ex-Seleka and anti- 
balaka fighters during two two-week missions in October 
and November and early December 2013 to the Central 
African Republic. The research team conducted interviews 
in the capital, Bangui; Bossangoa, the provincial capital 
of Ouham; and in towns and villages around Bossangoa, 
including Ndjo, Zéré, Wikamo, and Ouham-Bac. 
BODORO 
■»«' 
fi 
GUETTE 
VILLAGES 
LOCATIONS IN THE REPORT 
OUHAM-BAC 
WKAMO 
BOSSANGOA 
+ 
VOTOVO 
ZERE 
■ T'  ^tfl 
.1* 
Ll ^1.. 
jY- 
--r^ 
.4^ 
rvv 
^^j. 
rir 
GBAKORA 
'X 
14THEYCAMET0KILL 


Ashatu Isa, a Muslim nomadic cattle herder, and the mother of five children, was forced to watch as 
anti-balakafighterscutthethroatsof her 3-year-old son, two boys, ages 10 and 14, and an adult 
relative - all the Muslim males in the cattle camp. November 2, 2013. 
© 2013 Marcus Bleasdale/VII for Human Rights Watch 
'^m 
h 
'i- 
té. 
J. 
j^ 

i\ 
i 
M 
i 
II. ANTI-BALAKA 
ABUSES AGAINST 
MUSLIM COMMUNITIES 
NEARBOSSANGOA 
Afterthe Seleka rebel coalition seized power in March 2013, they 
ruled largely unopposed for months, frequently conducting deadly 
attacks and otherwise instilling fear among the civilian population.* 
In September, anfi-balaka militias organized simultaneous assaults 
against isolated and poorly manned ex-Seleka posts in the larger 
trading centers in the countryside. Around the town of Bossangoa, 
300 kilometers north of Bangui, they targeted Muslim communities 
as well as ex-Seleka posts. 
During this time, the anti-balaka attacked nomadic cattle camps 
ofthe ethnic Peuhl Muslim community, causing many deaths and 
stealingat least 5,000 heads of cattle, a massive financial and 
cultural loss. 
Eric Zalo, a leader ofthe anti-balaka forces in Wikamo, told Human 
Rights Watch: 
We were originally organized to fight against the coupeurs de 
route [highway bandits]. In Wikamo, we have a committee of 8 
leaders and 213 fighters. Our objective is to fight against the 
Seleka because oftheir abuses againstthe civilian population. 
... We have our own homemade weapons. They are made by 
us and use shotgun shells.... The anti-balaka are exclusively 
Christian, and our aim is to liberate the Christian population 
from the yoke ofthe Muslims. We are nota rebel group, we only 
fight against the Seleka and protect the population. [We are the 
youth and] we organized ourselves for our own self-defense.^ 
While the anti-balaka describe themselves as self-defense 
forces aiming to protect their own villages, their actual behavior 
and rhetoric is often violently anti-Muslim, and they have been 
responsible for numerous massacres of Muslims. Muslim 
survivors of such massacres told Human Rights Watch of extremist 
statements made by anfi-balaka leaders duringthe attacks, 
includingthatthey aimed to kill all Muslims. While most anfi- 
4 Human Rights Watch, "I Can StillSmellthe Dead": The Forgotten Human Rights 
Crisis in the CentralAfrican Republic, September 2013. 
5 Human Rights Watch interview with Eric Zalo, executive committee member ofthe 
anti-balaka forces in Wikamo, November 2, 2013. 
16THEYCAMET0KILL 
THEYCAMETO KILL 17 
 

baiaka fighters are poorly armed with homemade shotguns, 
machetes, and knives, some ofthe attacks investigated 
by Human Rights Watch also involved attackers in military 
uniform with Kalashnikov assault rifies and other automatic 
weapons; they are believed to be former FACA military 
personnel who have remained loyal to ousted president 
Bozizé, including members of his elite Presidential Guard. 
Human Rights Watch witnessed large numbers of child 
soldiers in the ranks ofthe anti-balaka. An anti-balaka 
leader acknowledged to Human Rights Watch that his group 
uses children as young as 15-years-old as fighters, but not 
those under 15. However, duringthe interviewwith this 
anti-balaka leader. Human Rights Watch saw armed children 
who appeared to be younger than 15.' On a visit to the anti- 
balaka stronghold of Bowaye in early December, Human 
rights watch observed hundreds of armed children among 
the anti-balaka fighters, many of them clearly younger than 
15. 
The following section describes anti-balaka abuses in the 
area surrounding Bossangoa. 
ZÉRÉ 
Zéré is a major trading center on the Bossangoa-Bouca road, 
with a community of more than 100 Muslims living next 
to the mosque in the center of the town. Two independent 
witnesses told Human Rights Watch that at least 56 Muslim 
residents, both traders and Mbororo cattle herders, were 
killed during a September 6 attack by anti-balaka elements 
in the Muslim quarter ofthe town.^ 
According to the imam ofthe mosque, tensions rose inthe 
week before the September 6 attack, when anti-balaka 
members killed an Mbororo cattle herder in the nearby 
village of Boubou on August 31, and refused to hand over 
his body to the family.^ Ex-Seleka fighters attempted to get 
The wife and child ofthe local area chief of Zéré, Bouba Gal, take 
shelter from the insecurity in the villages surrounding Bossangoa. Anti- 
balaka forces killed her husband and 13-year-old son, burning their 
bodies and dumpingthem in a latrine. Novemberl, 2013. 
© 2013 Marcus Bleasdale/VII for Human Rights Watch 
6 Human Rights Watch interview with Eric Zalo, executive committee mem- 
ber of the anti-balaka forces in, Wikamo, November 2, 2013. 
7 Human Rights Watch interview with Imam Zakaria Mikael, Imam of Zéré, 
Bossangoa, November 2, 2013 (claiming 57 Muslims died in the attack); 
Human Rights Watch interviewwith Hamid Oumar, chefde quartier of Zéré, 
Bossangoa, October 31, 2013 (claiming 56 Muslims died in the attack). On 
the Mbororo, see Human Rights Watch, "I Can StillSmellthe Dead": The 
Forgotten Human Rights Crisis in the CentralAfrican Republic, September 
2013, http://www.hrw.org/reports/2013/09/18/i-can-still-smell-dead p. 
34 . Or for an anthropological account of Mbororo society, see Philip Burn- 
ham, The Politics of Cultural Difference in Northern Cameroon (Edinburg: 
Edinburg University Press, 1996). 
8 Human Rights Watch interview with Imam Zakaria Mikael, Imam of Zéré, 
Bossangoa, November 2, 2013. 
r /— 
J- 
I» 
^ 
/ 
r 

^ 
iC 
h 
*}i*m 
\ 
%sst 
> 
**" 
Jk 
i 
cPJ)!* 
'.J 
?* 
fl'^-.S^ 
/^ 
* 
Vi^ 
V 
^'^■y 
*!»'* 
18THEYCAMET0KILL 
THEYCAMETO KILL 19 


ZERE 
VILLAGE LOCATION: 5.660N 16.990E 
Satellite Image Date: November 14, 2013 
A market center located 25 
kilometers east of Bossangoa, 
Zéré's Muslim community and a 
small ex-Seleka presence were 
attacked by anti-balaka forces 
on September 6, resulting in the 
deaths of dozens and the burning 
ofthe town's Muslim quarter 
and its Mosque. Followingthe 
anti-balaka attack, ex-Seleka 
forces returned and burned the 
Christian homes. A total of 333 
buildings, representing 85% of 
the village, were destroyed by fire 
based on an analysis of satellite 
imagery recorded on the morning 
of November 14, 2013. Destroyed 
buildings visible in the image are 
circled in red. 
DESTROYED BUILDINGS 
•^T^^ 
Damage Analysis: Human Rights Watch; 
Satellite Sensor: Pléiades-IA; 
Image Copyright: CNES 2013; 
Source: Astrium. 
m 
** 
\%: 
m 
^V. 
*:f 
t 
V 
tl 
^-. J 
^ 
Â 
■if ^      f 
I z 1 
^, 
^é^^n^^^^^MBPm. 
^£^ 
j^ 
^j* 
k^ 
i 
<-! 
J 
#, 
^ 

^ 
imi 
^ 
v*^ 

i: 
*mi^ 

¥>■ 
■* 

:^..:J^-i 
ff^&f 
J^ 

'f*-^. 
».. 
^. 
4 
m 
VL^ 
G)^ 

m 
^^ 
*, -îl; 
5^^v/i^*^: 
.'-* *i 
*oâ 
-t 
« 
-A 
« 
t' 
f^' 
# 
a 
« 
^ 
^ 

^m 
^.Mm.M^m:m::^^ 
r. 
t^' 
*» 
èM 
^ 
P 
# 
» 
fV^^s^^ 
/• 
li) 
Ü5 
# 
•rf 
(i 
>*•- ,- 
« 
r 
,i-3i 
fe 
J3 
m 
'ê 
'AA 
ü« 
î^?i^:^^^^^ 
tJl 
>®^1 
t- 
.f 
e 
^ 
'£lV 
» 
V>i 
i 
* 
» 
^ 
r*;^ « 
» 
m 
m 
^ 
A; 
.-s- f ■: ■ 
1« 
S 
m 
I -1 
# 
:< 
* * 
^ 
» 
i.. 
J^ 
# 
«^ 
* 
/ 
^ 
i^ 
i* ' 
JW 
ç*ti^ 
<*.'» 
t-j 
?n 
,^ -11^' 
@ 
» 
(I 
^ 
^ 
.% 
ft 
t^ 
«^ 
« 
Vis 
^ 
>0>;t; 
*j' 
^ 
^ 
4 
5* 
I* 
äM 
/% 

V*' 
^ 
i* 
^ 
^ 
3- 
_>«< 
.s» 
■^ 
iUÎt 
if 
£) 

t 
ik 
® 
f 
'i. 
^' 
® 
c 
^*^ 
€^ 
*f 
if 
.^. 
^ 
V   » 
■*^ 
*r. 
/»■ 
w* 
® 
<.^3^rf^ii 
^ 
* 
¥: 
h i 
s 
^ 
^ 
dl 
« 
^ 
é 
^ 
® 
3i^:V:Ä. 
S.f* 
lf 
S 
^(4-. 
'^ 
® 
*^'î*i^ 
'iiHf 
# 
V 
^ 
# 
K^, 
:, '^.  ,c 
-J 
t   .   'M! 
î€r 
4-^ 
* * 
_    o 
.^îffi;^î 
ft. 
-ij 

1^ 
® 
■^ 
♦t 
^ 
*f 
« 
i 

^«'^=«3^©* 
I 
"A 
^ 
.») 
^- 
^« 
im\ 
'     A 
^-•f 
« 
■*^ - 
^ 
^» 
^. 
D 
'H 
® 
« 
frt*< 
J^ 
4 

*4 
« 
f 
# 
'       '. 
% 
H»^; 
* 
#* 
* 
^ 
il 
'^ 
^ 
? 
•<* 
^* 
at^ 
W 
^ 
fk 
^i 
1-î 
jç. 
r* 
■tM 
^ 
[tfî 
« 
1 
ï? 
i#t 
«u 
P'.' 
Jf 
#^ 
ir 
TT 
i 
1 
t 
*s* 
r 
A^ 
i* 
£ 
:.** 
* 
♦ 
rï^ 
« 
J*- 
20THEYCAMETO KILL 
THEYCAMETO KILL21 


the body by force, but were ambushed by the anti-balaka 
and retreated to Zéré, where they had a post manned by 
five ex-Seleka fighters.'The presence ofthe ex-Seleka 
fighters in Zéré caused most Christians to leave the town, 
and only Muslim residents remained.^" 
The imam told Human Rights Watch that on the 
morning of September 6, about 100 anti-balaka quickly 
overpowered the ex-Seleka post, killingtwo ex-Seleka 
fighters and forcing the remaining three to fiee. They then 
turned on Zéré's Muslim community: 
At 4 a.m., we were attacked by the [anti-balaka] 
armed elements. We heard the gunshots, and atfirst 
thought itwas the Seleka firing. But then we heard 
them yelling, "Advancel Advancel" We were at the 
mosque, praying. We heard them shout, "Catch theml 
Catch theml (attraper)" I saw them shoot Abdullahi, 
an Mbororo herder. Then they went to the house of 
Abdullahi jibo—they killed him, his wife, his son, his 
daughter, and five Mbororo who were living with them. 
They went to the house ofthe area chief Bouba Gai, 
and killed him and his son Halidou. They burned their 
bodies and threw them in a latrine.... They looted our 
houses and then burned them. We counted 57people 
killed, including 17 Muslims from the town, and the 
restwere Mbororo killed in the bush with their cattle." 
The wife ofthe killed area chief confirmed the imam's 
account ofthe attack in a separate interview with Human 
Rights Watch: 
Itwas around 5 a.m. when they attacked our house. I 
was busy cooking outside. The anti-balaka came and 
attacked us. They began to cut my husband with their 
machetes on his side and his back, and cut his throat. 
After they killed him, they set our house on fire, and 
threw his body on the fire, together with that of my 
son. They ordered my 13-year-old boy, Halidou Bouba, 
to come outside and lay down, and then cut him two 
times with a machete and killed him. ...They also killed 
Bouba Mana Othman. He was on his bike near Zéré 
when they killed him with a machete. We found his 
9 Ibid. 
10 Human Rights Watch interview with Imam Zakaria Mikael, Imam of 
Zéré, Bossangoa, November 2, 2013; Human Rights Watch interview 
with Hamid Oumar, chefde quartier of Zéré, Bossangoa, October 31, 
2013. 
11  Human Rights Watch interview with Imam Zakaria Mikael, Imam of 
Zéré, Bossangoa, November 2, 2013. 
22THEYCAMET0KILL 
body... They killed the village chief Abdullahi Jibo, 
with three members of his family. 
Followingthe attack, the surviving Muslims, fearing more 
attacks, fied into the bush. The area chief's wife said: 
/ fled with my children into the bush and was there for 
two months. I just came to Bossangoa a few days ago. 
My three-year-old son was wounded bya machete. I 
told the attackers I was [Christian] and begged them to 
let me go, and they believed me. I changed my boy and 
dressed him as a girl to prevent him being killed. " 
She told Human Rights Watch that her 14-year-old 
daughter, Bouba Kandé, had been abducted bythe anti- 
balaka fighters and remained missing, as was her co-wife 
and her co-wife's 3-year-old daughter." 
Two days later, ex-Seleka fighters returned to Zéré. The 
Muslim residents who returned found their mosque and 
homes burned, with many ofthe Muslims killed having 
been thrown by the anti-balaka into the fiâmes ofthe 
burning homes.^* On a November visit to Zéré, Human 
Rights Watch counted more than 340 homes burned 
in the town, with only a handful of homes remaining 
undamaged. 
Zéré's imam was careful to stress to Human Rights Watch 
that he did not see the violence in the town as rooted in 
religion: 
This was nota Christian-Muslim attack; itwas an 
attack by Bozizé loyalists. There were more than 
100 attackers, they came from all sides. They had 
military weapons among them and included ex-FACA 
that defected and organized with the anti-balaka. 
They misled the Christian villagers, telling them that 
... there should be no more Muslims present in the 
country." 
GBAKORA/BANDOROK 
Gbakora and Bandorok are small villages on the 
Bossombélé-Bossangoa road, located about 45 
12 Human Rights Watch interviewwith a resident of Zéré village, 
Bossangoa, Novemberl, 2013. 
13 Ibid. 
14 Human Rights Watch interview with Imam Zakaria Mikael, Imam of 
Zéré, Bossangoa, November 2, 2013; Human Rights Watch interview with 
Hamid Oumar, chefde quartier of Zéré, Bossangoa, October 31, 2013. 
15  Ibid. 
^ 
^% 
^ 
Èk- 
W^ 
^ 
•^^..^ 
#1 
â', 
ij-ii 
kilometers south of Bossangoa. According to a Muslim 
resident who witnessed the attack, 11 Muslim families 
lived in the area, and there were no ex-Seleka fighters 
present. The Muslim residents began to hear rumors that 
the anfi-balaka were preparing to attack their community. 
Muslim residents sent a representative to Bossangoa on 
September 10 to ask ex-Seleka fighters to come protect 
them, but the ex-Seleka fighters turned down the request, 
saying they had no fighters or vehicles to spare." 
On September 11, over 100 anfi-balaka fighters, armed with 
homemade hunfing rifies and machetes, attacked Muslim 
villagers in Gbakora and Bandorok. A Muslim witness said 
the villages' Chrisfian residents assisted the anfi-balaka 
fighters in finding the homes of Muslims in the villages.^^ 
A 20-year-old Mbororo resident of Bandoroktold Human 
Rights Watch how the attackers had killed 11 Muslims: 
They began attacking the Muslims, and the Christian 
16 Human Rights Watch interview with [name withheld], Bossangoa, 
Novemberl, 2013. 
17 Human Rights Watch interview with a resident of Bandorok, Bossan- 
goa, November 1, 2013. 
A bumed mosque in Zéré. Hundreds of Christian and Muslim homes 
and places of worship were destroyed in the town during a series of 
attacks by both ex-Seleka and anti-balaka forces. November 4, 2013. 
© 2013 Marcus Bleasdale/VII for Human Rights Watch 
villagers who were still in the village helped the 
anti-balaka find the houses of Muslims. I saw them 
shoot two people in front of me. They were shot with 
homemade hunting rifies. Itwas IdrissAdef our 
village chief 75, and Zakaria Ibrahim, 80—they had 
machetes to defend themselves but were shotdead. 
Eleven people were killed in total. They also killed 
Oumar Idriss, 40, the son ofthe village chief; two 
brothers Hassan and Ibrahim Rama, ages 42 and 
35; Isein Wadai, 75, the deputy imam, and his son 
Shaibu, 30, and three Mbororo nomads who were 
visiting our village and whose names I don't know.^^ 
He managed to escape into the bush, where he hid until 
a convoy of ex-Seleka fighters arrived from Bossombelé, 
causing the anti-balaka fighters and Chrisfian villagers 
to fiee. He helped locate and bury the bodies of his 
fellow Muslim residents of the village before fieeing to 
Bossangoa for safety." 
This resident of Bandoroksaid that many ofthe 
Muslim residents remain missing. They include Khadija 
18 Ibid. 
19 Ibid. 
THEYCAMETO KILL23 


Abdullahi, the wife of Oumar Idriss (the son ofthe village 
chief killed in the attack) and her four children, as well 
as the wife of his surviving brother Jamal Idriss, Cecile 
Djumal, 30, and herthree children.^" 
OUHAM-BAC 
Ouham-Bac is a major trading center on the Bossangoa- 
Bozoum road, and many ofthe shops in the town's 
market are owned by Muslim traders. A resident of 
Ouham-Bac, 54, told Human Rights Watch that she was 
at home when anti-balaka fighters attacked the small ex- 
Seleka post in the town on September 6. The anti-balaka 
killed two ex-Seleka fighters before attacking Muslim 
homes. The anfi-balaka fighters shot dead Moamar's 
21-year-old nephew, Hassan Abaker, in front of his 
house, and also killed Haroon, a 30-year-old Christian 
who had converted to Islam. She went into hiding aft:er 
seeingthetwo killings.^^ 
BODORA 
A resident of Bodora, 55, was at his home in Bodora 
village, northeast of Bossangoa on the Bir Zambé road, 
when he was awakened at about 5 a.m. on September 6 
by gunfire. Outside, he found two half-dressed women in 
a state of panic, one of whom he recognized as the wife 
of an ex-Seleka colonel based nearby. The women told 
him that anti-balaka fighters were attacking. 
As the family prepared to fiee, anti-balaka fighters 
arrived. He managed to escape into high grass near his 
home, but then watched in horror as the anti-balaka 
fighters cut the throats of his family members and others 
next to the bridge between Ben Zambé and Bodora. He 
told Human Rights Watch: 
[The attackers] were numerous, and they were armed 
with Kalashnikovs, guns, machetes, and knives. They 
caughtall of mychildren. I managed to run away and 
hide in the tall grass. I saw them cut the throats of my 
children, one by one, with a knife. They passed the 
children to the one who had the knife, one by one.... 
After the children, they killed my wives, and then more 
people, people they had caught in the neighborhood. 
There were bodies everywhere, they left them there.^^ 
20 Ibid. Human Rights Watch interview with [name withheld], Bossan- 
goa, November 1, 2013. 
21  Human Rights Watch interviewwith a resident of Ouham-Bac, 
Bossangoa, Novemberl, 2013. 
22 Human Rights Watch interviewwith a resident of Bodora, Bossan- 
24THEYCAMETO KILL 
Among those killed were his two wives, Bali Gouro, 37, and 
Modari Modjolo, 37, and his 11 children and grandchild: 
Rouha, 25; Abou, 20; Minieko, 16, and her daughter Hawa, 
6 months; Souleh, 15; Halima, 14; Mayro, 13; Seydou, 13; 
Biba, 10; Saaleh, 10, and Djouli, 8." This witness appeared 
to be the sole survivor from this attack. He recognized some 
ofthe leaders ofthe anti-balaka as villagers from near his 
home. They included a Christian cattle raiser from Bondora 
who suffered the loss of all of his cattle by ex-Seleka forces 
and had vowed revenge.^* 
Aft:erwatching his family murdered, he hid in the bush for 
two days before seeking shelter with a wealthy Christian in 
a neighboring village whom he knew well. The Chrisfian man 
told him he could stay with him. From the window ofthe 
house, this witness could see the activity of a nearby anti- 
balaka base: 
From the window of [my Christian friend's] house, I could 
see the base ofthe anti-balaka, in a building covered 
with white tarps. I could see them come back in the 
evening with loads of meat, which they shared with all 
ofthe people in the village. They brought [abducted 
people] to their chief who was sometimes in civilian 
clothes and sometimes in military clothes—they brought 
him [abducted] Muslims. Sometimes, I could hear their 
screams, and then nothing, and sometimes they let them 
live. But I couldn 'tsee how they killed them, because 
there were too many people around—however, I think 
they killed many people there in the five days I was 
hiding.^'' 
On the sixth day of his hiding, ex-Seleka fighters arrived and 
forced the anti-balaka forces to fiee the village.^* 
VOTOVO 
A Muslim cattle raiser, 24, resident ofVotovo, told Human Rights 
Watch that dozens of anfi-balaka fighters attacked the Muslim 
areas of his village ofVotovo, located 15 kilometers south of 
Bossangoa, at about 5 a.m. on September 26: 
/ was at my home. I heard loud noises and gunfire 
outside. Itwas the anti-balaka ofthe Gbaya tribe, several 
dozen of them. They were speaking their language. They 
were armed with Kalashnikovs, machetes, and their 
goa, Novembers, 2013. 
23 Ibid 
24 Ibid. 
25 Ibid. 
26 Ibid. 
homemade hunting guns. They came on foot, and 
entered all ofthe houses. At my house, they looted my 
clothes, my luggage, and my kitchen utensils. Then 
they gathered all of us at the square ofthe village, 
and told us, "We will kill all the Muslims, and first 
we will kill all your livestock. " Then, they separated 
the [Muslim] men on one side, and the women and 
children on the otherside.^^ 
After separating the men from the women, about a 
dozen attackers overpowered the cattle raiser's older 
brother, 27-year-old Amadou Hiroyi, and cut his throat 
with a knife, killing him. They then opened fire with their 
homemade guns on the rest ofthe Muslim men there. 
Two Muslim men and a Muslim boy were killed by the 
gunfire - Amadou Djibo, 20; Adam Bouba, 18; and Ade 
Djibo, 13. The rest fied fortheir lives.^^ 
A second resident ofVotovo, 32, separately told Human 
Rights Watch: 
They took all of us [Muslims] to the village square 
and said, "We are going to kill you all. " I asked them, 
"Why?" Their chief said, "Who told you to talk? We 
are going to kill all the Mbororo because you are all 
Muslims. And we will kill all your livestock. " I watched 
them cut the throat of Amadou Hiroyi, and then they 
killed [shot] my two little brothers as we were running 
away-Amadou Djibo, 20, and Ade Djibo, 13.^^ 
He and the other surviving men fied into the bush, but 
returned at night to see what had happened to their 
village. They found all oftheir homes burned, and all 
of their cattle slaughtered, with only the inedible heads 
remaining.^" Twenty-one Muslim women and children who 
had been separated from the men were missing. None 
had been found atthefime of Human Rights Watch's visit 
in early November, nearly two months afterthe attack and 
were presumed dead by their relatives.^^ The surviving 
27 Human Rights Watch interviewwith a resident ofVotovo, Bossan- 
goa, Novembers, 2013. His accountof the attack was confirmed by 
several other Votovo residents interviewed by Human Rights Watch. 
Human Rights Watch interviews with residents of Votovo, Bossangoa, 
Novembers, 2013. 
28 Ibid. 
29 Human Rights Watch interviewwith a resident ofVotovo, Bossan- 
goa, Novembers, 2013. 
30 Human Rights Watch interviewwith a resident ofVotovo, Bossan- 
goa, Novembers, 2013. 
31 The 21 missing include 17 children: Zakaria Barka, 7; Shaibou 
Bouba, 7; Halidou Barka, 5; Hamadou Seini, 8; Moussa Seini, 5; Abassi 
Bouba, 13; Kaltoumi Diibo, 16; Diouli Bouba, 10; Salma Bella, 17; 
Muslim men spent five days hiding in the bush around the 
village before being rescued by ex-Seleka fighters led by 
General Ali, who had come from Bossangoa after receiving 
reports about the attack on the village.^^ 
BOSSANGOA 
On December 5, anti-balaka forces mounted a major 
attack on Bossangoa itself, briefly seizing control ofthe 
town. Duringthe attack, anti-balaka forces killed Muslim 
civilians in the Muslim Boro quarter of Bossangoa, killing 
at least 11 civilians with machetes and gunfire. Among 
the dead was Ousman Abacar, 26, ayoung Peuhl whom 
Human Rights Watch had taken to the hospital that same 
morning to obtain treatment for a gunshot wound he had 
received three weeks earlier during an anti-balaka attack 
on the cattle camp where he lived, north of Bossangoa. 
Ousman Abacar was unable to fiee the anti-balaka 
attackers because ofthe wound, and was captured and 
killed by having his throat cut.^^ His mother, who had 
stayed behind to take care of him, was also killed.^* 
Nine other Muslims lost their lives, including Khadija 
Ine, 35, the wife ofthe Muslim trader Gara Iné, and her 
brother Adei Abacar, 38, who were also caught and killed 
by having their throats cut nearthe house ofthe imam, 
where they had sought safety.^^ 
It was a surprise attack, so everyone fied to the 
imam's house for safety, and it is around there that so 
many were killed. The people who attacked included 
real FACA soldiers and Presidential Guards, armed 
with AK-47S and RPGs [rocket-propelled grenades], 
and theywere in uniform and wearing the red berets 
[ofthe former presidential guard].^^ 
Diala Bouba, 13; Fadi Bouba, 10; Hawa Seini, 13, and her two sisters 
Hamina Seini, 4, and Fane Seini, 8 months; Fadi Baraka, 7; Kaltouma 
Baraka, 2; and Ade Diibo, 5. Four adult women are also missing: Lady 
Sankara, 50, and her two daughters Gueba Diibo, 25, and DJidia Diibo, 
20; and Diidiia Bouba, 30 (the wife of Adam Bouba, who was shot 
dead). 
32 Human Rights Watch interviewwith a resident of Votovo, Bossangoa, 
Novembers, 2013. 
33 Human Rights Watch interviewwith Ousman Abacar, Bossangoa, 
December 5, 2013. Human Rights Watch interviewwith Boro resident, 
Bossangoa, December 6, 2013. 
34 Ibid. 
35 Human Rights Watch interviewwith Boro resident, Bossangoa, 
December 6, 2013. 
36 Ibid. 
THEYCAMETO KILL25 


The other dead from the incident included Qursi 
Abdulrahim, 50, trader; Ali Atahir, 45,trader; Jimey Atahir, 
42, trader; Aishta Oumar, 38, a mother of three children; 
Nami Yawa, an Mbororo mother with four children; her 
sister Hawa Yama, an Mbororo mother with six children; and 
Hamidou "Seize-Dix-Sept," a popular motorcycle taximan.^^ 
Beldo Ibrahim holds her daughter who survived an attack with ma- 
chetes and knives by anti-balaka militias, who killed her husband 
and three boys, ages 3,10, and 14. November 2, 2013. 
© 2013 Marcus Bleasdale/VII for Human Rights Watch 
ATTACKS ON MBORORO CATTLE 
CAMPS 
At the same time as the attacks on ex-Seleka outposts 
and bases and Muslim communities in BirZambé, Zere, 
Ouham-Bac, and Koro M'Poko, anti-balaka forces also 
conducted attacks on Muslim-owned cattle camps run by 
Mbororo herders in the same regions, stealing thousands 
of heads of cattle and killingmany ofthe Mbororo 
families who were guarding the cattle. 
A Mbororo woman in her late thirties was at a cattle 
camp of some 500 cows located 13 kilometers from Bir 
Zambé when it was attacked by anti-balaka forces on 
September 6. The attackers included both lightly armed 
anti-balaka fighters and well-armed military defectors.^^ 
The attackers shot dead her husband, Abubaker Bouba; 
his second wife Adama Yahiya; this witness's three 
children, Oumar, Zeituna, and Jambrila; and the five 
children of her co-wife, Abasi,Aisatu, Fadi, Rahmatu, 
and Adamour.^^' She herself was wounded with a bullet 
to the back of her head, and she lost consciousness 
duringthe attack. The owner ofthe cattle found 
her barely alive more than a week later, amid the 
decomposing remains of her family,and brought her 
to Bossangoa for medical treatment.*" He told Human 
Rights Watch that anti-balaka forces killed six of the 
nine Mbororo guards, and stole 747 heads of cattle at 
the neighboring cattle camp belongingto his brother 
Nazal Mohammed. All 500 of his cattle had been stolen, 
he lamented.*^ 
El-Nour Adim, 51, a wealthy Muslim businessman, heard 
aboutthe attacks on the camps and asked ex-Seleka 
37 Ibid. 
38 Human Rights Watch interviewwith Hadiia Oumar, Bossangoa, 
October 31, 2013; Human Rights Watch interviewwith Daoud 
Mohammed, Bossangoa, October 31, 2013. 
39 Human Rights Watch interview with [name withheld], Bossangoa, 
October 31, 2013. This woman, who was still recovering from a gunshot 
wound to the head, was too weakto recount the ages ofthe dead 
during the interview with Human Rights Watch. 
40 Human Rights Watch interview with [name withheld], Bossangoa, 
October 31, 2013. 
41  Ibid. 
26THEYCAMET0KILL 
n,    ¥   *:   r / ^ 
\ 
"-> 
J 
> 
^_ 
\ 
m 
'é 
k 
%-.. 
m^ 
■:^^^ 

1»:'^ 
1 .< 
:^ 
It         ■     4 
THEYCAMETO KILL27 


forces to escort him to his cattle camp near BirZambé 
to check. On the road, the convoy was ambushed by 
the anti-balaka, and El-Nour Adim and two ofthe seven 
ex-Seleka fighters accompanying him were killed in the 
attack.*^ When Adim's younger brother finally managed 
to reach the camp site nearly a month later, he found 
the skeletal remains of all 12 Mbororo family members: 
five adult Mbororo and their seven children who had 
been guarding the camp. The 406 head of cattle were all 
missing.« 
A Mbororo woman, 32, was with 10 other Mbororo at the 
cattle camp ofa Muslim businessman. Gara Iné, who 
lost his wife and brother-in-law duringthe December 
5 anfi-balaka attack on Bossangoa (see above). She 
was coming back to the cattle camp at about 4 p.m. on 
September 6 from gathering food, when the camp came 
under attack from a large group of anti-balaka fighters: 
"The anti-balaka were so many, like a whole village of 
them."*'' The anti-balaka fighters surprised and captured 
all 11 Mbororo in the camp and proceeded to separate 
the men from the women, before killing the men. She 
told Human Rights Watch: 
They put us on the ground, and then said theywould 
kill the males only. They told us to remove our shoes. 
There were a lot of them [anti-balaka], and then they 
pushed the four males down and cut their throats in 
front of us. One was my husband, Yaya Douka. The 
others were just children: Bouba Keriyo, 14, Tahirou 
Keriyo, 10, and Khalidou Ngadjo, 3. Even the children 
had their throats cut. My daughter Habiba, 3, was hit 
on her head with a machete, and cut all over her back 
with knives—she was in her father's hands so they 
thought she was a boy.*^ 
An Mbororo woman in her forties who was the mother 
ofthe 3-year-old boy killed in the attack, Halaidu Ndajo, 
42 Human Rights Watch interviewwith [name withheld], Bossangoa, 
October 31, 2013. 
43 Ibid. 
44 Human Rights Watch interview with [name withheld], Bossangoa, 
Novemberl, 2013; Human Rights Watch interviewwith [name 
withheld], Bossangoa, October 31, 2013. 
45 Human Rights Watch interviewwith [name withheld], Bossangoa, 
Novemberl, 2013. 
28THEYCAMET0KILL 
confirmed the details ofthe incident in a separate 
interview with Human Rights Watch. She told Human 
Rights Watch: 
There were lots of attackers. They had AK-47s as well as 
machetes and homemade rifles. Some of them were in 
military uniforms. They came and trapped me with my 
child. They killed my boy and three others—they had all 
four captive, and executed them one by one, next to the 
river. They said it was the Muslims who chased away 
Bozizé, and so now all the Muslims will suffer until the 
end. They killed my child in front of me. 
Then the night came, and some of them said they 
wouldn't kill the women and so they let us go. We left to 
hide in the bush. But then there was an argument, and 
some said they had to kill us as well. So they came to 
search for us, but we stayed hidden, me and my sister.** 
Qursi Mohammad, a Muslim trader, 46, stayed with his 
156 cattle ata camp near Zéré, togetherwith an Mbororo 
cattle herder. On September 7, anti-balaka fighters 
attacked the camp and shot dead Qursi and his Mbororo 
cattle herder and stole the cattle. The next day, ex-Seleka 
forces and Muslim traders from Bossangoa found the 
two bodies.*^ According to the owner, an adjacent cattle 
camp housing 176 head of cattle was looted at the same 
fime, and the Mbororo herder was also shot dead.*^ 
Human Rights Watch found many more similar cases of 
Muslim-owned cattle camps around Bossangoa that were 
attacked by anti-balaka elements in September 2013, 
including additional cases where Mbororo herders at the 
camps were killed. The Muslim business community of 
Bossangoa prepared a list of 21 Muslim-owned cattle 
camps that were raided, counting nearly 5,000 heads 
of cattle looted, a massive financial, social, and cultural 
loss for this largely nomadic community.*' 
EX-SELEKA ABUSES 
AGAINST CHRISTIANS 
46 Human Rights Watch interview with [name withheld], Bossangoa, 
November 2, 2013. 
47 Human Rights Watch interview with [name withheld], Bossangoa, 
October 31, 2013. The witness did not know the name ofthe Mbororo 
cattle herder who had been killed in the incident. 
48 Human Rights Watch interview with [name withheld], Bossangoa, 
October 31, 2013. 
49 List provided to Human Rights Watch, November 1, 2013. 
The September attacks bythe anti-balaka on ex-Seleka 
forces in the Bossangoa region resulted in significant ex- 
Seleka losses. Many oftheir smaller outposts and bases 
in places such as Ouham-Bac, Zéré, Bowali, and Bir 
Zambé were quickly overrun bythe more numerous anti- 
balaka forces. As a result, the ex-Seleka abandoned most 
ofthe countryside around Bossangoa and concentrated 
their remaining fighters in the main population center of 
Bossangoa. 
Followingthese setbacks, ex-Seleka forces responded 
by carrying out deadly attacks on the villages where the 
attacks had occurred and burning down some villages. 
Anti-balaka forces tried to protect Christian communities 
and their own militias from ex-Seleka retaliation. The 
anfi-balaka, for example, destroyed bridges on the roads 
around Bossangoa, effectively preventing ex-Seleka 
movement there. 
Ex-Seleka forces have continued to instill fear in areas 
by conducting surprise attacks targefing small groups 
of Christians. There are 40,000 Christians who have 
fied the countryside and sought out the relative safety 
ofthe Catholic church in Bossangoa, where they live in 
cramped and overcrowded conditions. Any travel outside 
the camp to other parts ofthe city orto their fields, 
however, is dangerous, especially for men. 
Attacks on Christians in Bossangoa have taken place with 
complete impunity and with the consent, and in some 
cases direct participation, ofthe highest-ranking ex- 
Seleka commanders in Bossangoa. On November 18, at 
about 5 p.m., ex-Seleka forces detained seven Christian 
farmers nearthe airport in Bossangoa as they attempted 
to return from a day's work in their fields. The men were 
tied up and brought to the camp of General Yaya, the 
ex-Seleka commander of Bossangoa. ''° According to a 
survivor, the tied-up men were brought before General 
Yaya and his then-deputy commander. Colonel Saleh, 
and about a dozen other senior commanders, and 
presented as captured anti-balaka fighters. The deputy 
commander. Colonel Saleh, in the presence of General 
Yaya personally ordered his men to "throw them in 
the river."" General Yaya was killed in the December 5 
fighting in Bangui, and his former deputy Colonel Saleh 
is now the commander of ex-Seleka in Bossangoa. 
One ofthe survivors told Human Rights Watch: 
At 3 a.m. they came with a vehicle. They tied us up 
even tighter and threw us into the vehicle, puta tarp 
over us, and took us to their main base, next to the 
UNICEF compound. Atthe base, they showed us to 
Colonel Saleh who came to see us. He authorized 
them to take us to the river and kill us. They spoke 
among themselves in Arabic, which I understood 
a bit General Yaya was there as well, with Colonel 
Saleh.... The meeting to decide our fate tooksome 25 
minutes. Itwas starting to become light soon, so they 
were in a hurry." 
The ex-Seleka fighters tookthe bound men to the Ouham 
River and threw two into the river nearthe radio station, 
but managed to free themselves and swim to safety aft:er 
the ex-Seleka fighters left. The five other bound men 
were taken by carlo the main bridge overthe Ouham 
River, and thrown into the swift-moving current. 
One ofthe survivors told Human Rights Watch: 
They took us to the bridge over the Ouham River. 
They took out three of us and began to beat them. 
Then they tied them up, and they bashed them on the 
concrete before throwing them into the river. Then 
they took the fourth person; they beat him until he 
was bleeding from his ears and nose. They were busy 
tying him up when he moved a bit, so they figured he 
was still too conscious to drown. They lifted him up 
and threw him down on the cement to stun him. Then 
they threw him into the river. 
50 General Yaya was killed on December 4 during an attack by anti- 
balaka in Bangui. 
51  Human Rights Watch interview with [name withheld], November 28, 
2013. 
52  Human Rights Watch interviewwith survivor of drowning incident 
[name withheld], December 5, 2013. Human Rights Watch conducted 
in-depth interviews with all three ofthe survivors. 
THEYCAMETO KILL29 


/ was the fifth person, the last one. They began to 
beat me on the head and body with their rifle butts, 
and my whole face was bloody. They thought I was 
unconscious. They had no more rope, so they tied me 
up with my pants and threw me into the river. They 
first threw me down on the cement fioor and then 
rolled me into the river. I rose to the surface and could 
see they were following me with their rifles. I went 
under three times and then my pants came loose and I 
managed to swim to the shore." 
On November 26, local humanitarian workers found the 
bodies ofthe four bound men on the banks ofthe river.^* 
ATTACKS INSIDE BOSSANGOA 
On September 10, Donacien Ndakuzu, a driver's 
assistant, went to the Bossangoa bus station to watch 
over his employer's vehicle, which was parked there. 
Accordingto Ndakuzu's wife, who spoke to those 
who witnessed the incident, three ex-Seleka fighters 
approached him at the station and demanded that he 
give them fuel from the vehicle. Ndakuzu explained 
to the ex-Seleka the vehicle had no fuel, but they 
threatened to kill him if he did not produce any. They 
then fired three rounds at him, killing him, and then 
walked back to their base, leaving his body behind." 
On the morning of September 14, Nesta Ngaipo, 38, a 
butcher, was on his way to the Bossangoa market with 
two Muslim helpers, carrying the meat of a cow he had 
just butchered. On the way they were stopped bythree 
ex-Seleka fighters who accused Ngaipo of being with the 
anti-balaka. The ex-Seleka let the two Muslim helpers 
go, but Ngaipo disappeared and is believed by his wife 
and his employees to have been killed by them.^* On 
September 15, a resident of Bossangoa, 35, was washing 
her clothes in the Ouham River in Bossangoa with her 
husband and her infant, when five ex-Seleka fighters 
approached them. She told Human Rights Watch how 
the ex-Seleka fighters opened fire on them, killing her 
husband while he was holdingtheirbaby in his hands: 
53 Ibid. 
54 Ibid. 
55 Human Rights Watch interviewwith [name withheld], Bossangoa, 
Novemberl, 2013. 
56 Human Rights Watch interview with [name withheld], Bossangoa, 
Novemberl, 2013. 
30THEYCAMETO KILL 
/ was busy washing our clothes in the river, and my 
husband was holding our baby. He told me, "Hurry, the 
Seleka are comingi" It was already too late. They fired a 
firstshotthathitmygirl in the arm, and then a second 
one that just brushed its head. My husband raised 
our daughter above his head to show he was carrying 
a child, and they fired again at him, hitting him in 
the stomach.... I acted as if I was dead. They wanted 
to come and check on me, but two ofthe Seleka said 
not to bother. I had to remain still forseveral hours, 
because theywere right above me. My little girl was 
bleeding heavily and crying. Finally, I came out, and 
they allowed me to take her to the hospital." 
On September 17, clashes broke out inside Bossangoa 
between ex-Seleka and anti-balaka fighters, catching 
many residents in the town by surprise and causing 
many to fiee. Duringthe clashes, indiscriminate gunfire 
occurred in many districts of Bossangoa, killing an 
unknown number of people. Several people told Human 
Rights Watch that ex-Seleka fighters responded to the 
anti-balaka attack on their Bossangoa positions by firing 
at civilians. 
In the Sembe neighborhood, ex-Seleka fighters shooting 
indiscriminately killed Ester Kandona, 35, who was eight- 
months pregnant, as she was working in their fields 
with herhusband.^^ "Seleka fighters were firing in all 
directions, and one ofthe bullets hit and killed her [and 
the fetus]," Kandona's sister-in-law told Human Rights 
Watch, "We fied to the church camp the same day."^' 
A resident of Bossangoa, 23, was also in the Sembe 
neighborhood of Bossangoa when ex-Seleka forces started 
firing. She hid inside her home for a while and then fied 
to the church camp. Her brother Alphonse Mondoka, 53, 
stayed inside his home, hiding under his bed. The next 
morning, Justine found Alphonse's dead body in front of 
his house with a gunshot wound in his back.*" 
Another resident of Bossangoa, 65, was at his home with 
a relative named Jeannot on September 17 when gunfire 
broke out in their Bossangoa neighborhood of Tipoyeur. 
57 Human Rights Watch interview with [name withheld], Bossangoa, 
Novembers, 2013. 
58 Human Rights Watch interview with [name withheld], Bossangoa, 
Novembers, 2013. 
59 Ibid. 
60 Human Rights Watch interview with a resident of Sembe neighbor- 
hood in Bossangoa, Bossangoa, Novembers, 2013. 
a.- 
tf*, 
T^ 
r^ 
t 
^ 
y 
4i 
J-' 
^ 
s 
ifp«^ 
k 
*i 
^^ 
,* 
»tT 
v^, 
r;i! 
m 
«N 
!■;, 
They hid inside for most ofthe day. He told Human Rights 
Watch that "around 5 p.m., when the Muslims [ex-Seleka] 
became tired of shooting, we left to seek refuge atthe 
church."" As they fied, the two men were separated, and 
he heard a gunshot ring out behind him. "Jeannot never 
arrived at the church camp. It was too dangerous for men 
to return to the neighborhood, but the women went back 
and found his body. They asked the Red Cross and the 
FOMAC [African Union] troops to bury him."" 
At about 5 p.m. on September 17, Germain Ngaissonna, 
37, a father of eight, attempted to return to Bossangoa 
from his field outside town, believing the fighting 
had died down. As he crossed the main bridge into 
Bossangoa, ex-Seleka fighters demanded that he and 
three other men stop. While these three managed to run 
away, the ex-Seleka fighters apprehended Ngaissonna 
on the bridge and fatally stabbed him." By nightfall, five 
men had been stabbed to death bythe ex-Seleka fighters 
on the bridge. The next day, four ofthe bodies were 
A burned Pentecostal church in Zéré. Hundreds of 
Christian and Muslim homes and places of worship were 
destroyed in the town duringa series of attacks by both 
ex-Seleka and anti-balaka forces. November 4, 2013. 
© 2013 Marcus Bleasdale/VII for Human Rights Watch 
thrown in the Ouham River. FOMAC troops, at his wife's 
request, recovered Ngaissonna's body.** 
On Novemberl, a Christian man, 23, went to look for 
his missing pigs nearthe Bossangoa school, where 
displaced Muslims were living. At the school, a Muslim 
woman started yelling at him, and then asked the ex- 
Seleka fighters at the adjoining checkpoint to kill him, 
saying that his parents were anti-balaka. The ex-Seleka 
fighters began beating him with their rifie butts, and 
then brought a knife to cut his throat. He managed to 
break free and run off, narrowly missing being shot 
by the ex-Seleka fighters as he made his escape. The 
enfire incident took place in broad daylight, just 100 
meters away from a team of foreign journalists staying 
at the main guesthouse in Bossangoa housing UN and 
humanitarian workers." 
61  Human Rights Watch interviewwith a resident of Tipoyeur neighbor- 
dhood in Bossango, Bossangoa, Novembers, 2013. 
62 Ibid. 
63 Human Rights Watch interviewwith [name withheld], Bossangoa, 
Novemberl, 20013 
64 Ibid. 
65 Human Rights Watch interviewwith [name withheld], Bossangoa, 
THEYCAMETO KILL31 
 

On October 24, Thierry Demokossai, 40, was 
working with his neighbors in their fields in the Bali 
neighborhood of Bossangoa. His wife, 30, recounted to 
Human Rights Watch what happened when a group of ex- 
Seleka fighters came to the area at about 3 p.m.: 
The Seleka came on foot, there were four of them. 
They hid in the bushes and then opened fire on us. 
We were six in the field, and three were killed: my 
husband, and two of his neighbors. There was no 
argument or anything. They just came out ofthe 
bushes where theywere hiding and opened fire on 
us without any warning. My husband was shot in the 
back ofthe head, and the bullet came out the front, 
destroying his whole face.^^ 
Pregnant at the time of her husband's death, she gave 
birth to a baby boy the next day.*^ 
At about 10 a.m. on October 8, a group of ex-Seleka 
fighters went house-to-house through the Bonjili district 
of Bossangoa, killing and burning. A resident ofthe 
Bonjili district, 25, told Human Rights Watch that when 
the ex-Seleka approached her house, her husband, 
Alfred Fenjiro, 32, tried to hide undertheir bed, while she 
ran out ofthe house. Hiding nearby, she watched as the 
ex-Seleka fighters killed him: 
Three Seleka fighters came into the house, and I ran 
out into the bush while my husband remained in the 
house. They killed him with knives and then burned 
the house. I saw it with my own eyes, and I could hear 
the screams of my husband inside. 
Two other men from Bonjili were similarly stabbed to 
death, she also recounted: 
They killed three men that morning in Bonjili. This was 
the first time the Seleka came to our neighborhood, 
and they came to kill. I don't know why—there was no 
anti-balaka in our area. 
She went back to Bonjili the next day and found her 
husband's body inside their burned home, with stab 
wounds to the stomach, back, and neck." 
Novemberl, 2013; Human Rights Watch interviewwith foreign Journal- 
ist who witnessed incident, Bossangoa, Novemberl, 2013. 
66 Human Rights Watch interviewwith a resident of Bali neighborhood 
in Bossangoa, Bossangoa, Novemberl, 2013. 
67 Ibid. 
68 Human Rights Watch interview with a resident ofthe Bonjili district 
32THEYCAMET0KILL 
ATTACKS OUTSIDE BOSSANGOA 
In late September or early October, ex-Seleka forces 
arrived in the village of Bogouna, 18 kilometers northeast 
of Bossangoa." As soon as they arrived, at about 3 p.m., 
they fired into the airto force the villagers to fiee, and 
then began burningthe homes in the village.^" When the 
villagers returned afterthe attack, they found the body of 
Léon Oudedan, 64, in front of his home with a gunshot 
wound to his back.^^ 
On October 22, Valentin Nambobona, 46, the village chief 
of Tamkouru village, was working in his fields with his 
two wives. At about 11 a.m., a group of armed Muslim 
cattle herders moved their cows through the field. His 
wives fied, but Nambobona tried to retrieve his bicycle. 
The wives heard three gunshots from their hiding place, 
and when they returned to the field a few hours later, 
they found Nambobona's body with a gunshot wound to 
the head. As a result ofthe killing ofthe village chief, the 
entire village fied their homes for fear of more attacks." 
On October 10, four vehicles of ex-Seleka fighters from 
Bossangoa travelled down the road to Ouham-Bac, where 
an ex-Seleka base as well as local Muslim residents had 
been attacked and killed in early September (see above). 
As they drove towards Ouham-Bac, the ex-Seleka fighters 
repeatedly fired at fieeing civilians along the road. At the 
village of Wikamo, the passing ex-Seleka fighters shot 
dead Samuel Denamjora, 12, and three other villagers." 
Afterthe villagers had fied Wikamo, the ex-Seleka fighters 
left their vehicles and looted the local hospital and 
school, emptying both buildings. They then proceeded to 
burn down the enfire village of Wikamo.^* 
As the ex-Seleka fighters proceeded towards Ouham-Bac, 
they passed the home of Nicole Faranganda, 34, who had 
given birth to a baby girl the day before. Weakened from 
of Bossangoa, Bossangoa, Novemberl, 2013. 
69 The witness did not recall the exact date ofthe attack, estimating 
that it had occurred 'three weeks or one month' before she was 
interviewed on Novembers. However, accordingto satellite fire 
detection data, several villages on the same road were burned on 
September 27, slightly more than one month before the witness was 
interviewed by Human Rights Watch. 
70 Human Rights Watch interviewwith a resident of Bogouna, 
Bossangoa, Novembers, 2013. 
71  Ibid. 
72  Human Rights Watch interview with a resident of Tamkouru, Bossan- 
goa, Novemberl, 2013. 
73  Human Rights Watch interview with a resident of Wikamo, Wikamo, 
Novembers, 2013. 
74  Ibid.; Human Rights Watch interviewwith Eric Zalo, Wikamo, No- 
vembers, 2013. 
^ 
■■ 
Si^^^^l-a 
1- 
^       \ 
labor, Faranganda was slow in fieeing from the ex-Seleka 
fighters. They shot her dead just outside her house.^^ 
When the ex-Seleka fighters reached Ouham-Bac, they 
quickly emerged from theirvehicles and tried to trap as 
many ofthe surprised residents as possible, before killing 
them.^* Jean-Marie Sendamanou, 50, was shot dead in 
front of his wife, Philomene, before she was also shot and 
killed." Marceline Gandaboye, 35, was shot dead as she 
fied with her baby tied to her back." Hiller Redebonna, 
55, was fatally shot in front of his house." Gervais Berofi, 
28, was unable to fiee because he had lost a leg in an 
accident; he was shot dead.^" Gaston Sanbogai, 22, was 
blind and tried to hide in the high grass next to his hut; 
the ex-Seleka fighters found him, pulled him out, and 
executed him.^^ Alice Gandako, 60, the wife ofthe mayor 
75 Human Rights Watch interview with a resident of Wikamo (mother of 
victim Nicole Faraganda), Wikamo, Novembers, 2013. 
76 Human Rights Watch interviewwith residents of Ouham-Bac, Ouham- 
Bac, Novembers, 2013. 
77 Ibid. 
78 Ibid. 
79 Ibid. 
80 Ibid. 
81  Ibid. 
of Ouham-Bac, was executed in front of her home.^^ Marie 
Konamina, 50, and a youth nicknamed Pasteur, 28, were 
shot dead as they fied. Two children and an adult drowned 
in the Ouham River as they fied the attackers in panic: 
Martial Redebonna, 8, Diane Fokean, 2, and Diane's father 
Armand Fokean, 38, who jumped in after her to try and 
save her.^3 
The villagers from Ouham-Bac said the ex-Seleka forces 
who attacked them on October 10 were accompanied by 
at least three Muslim traders from Ouham-Bac, whom they 
identified by name to Human Rights Watch. The traders 
pointed out to the ex-Seleka fighters which homes to burn, 
using their in-depth knowledge ofthe village.^* The ex- 
Seleka fighters burned 35 homes in Ouham-Bac, before 
another group of ex-Seleka fighters from Bozoum arrived 
and apparently convinced the group from Bossangoa to 
withdraw.^^ 
82 Ibid. 
83 Human Rights Watch interviewwith a resident of Ouham-Bac (father of 
victim Martial Redebonna), Ouham-Bac, Novembers, 2013. 
84 Ibid. 
85 Ibid. The Bozoum ex-Seleka fighters had been attending a meeting 
with local villagers ata location not far away from Ouham-Bac atthe time 
THEYCAMETO KILL33 


WIKAMO 
VILLAGE COORDINATES: 6.445N, 17.232E 
Satellite Image Date: December 4, 2013 
Ï- 
/f-^ 
^-■: 
f 
%^- 
nt 
t 
W'*^ 
^ 
m 
f*r^../ 
<5î 
^. 
.. »3 

^^ 
•..--.   ,^. 
w, 
® 

% 
« 
® 
® 
® 
® 
d 
® 
»ê 
» 
¥-^ 
■.:.    [ 
iiT' 
.it ' i 
w^##^:^:-:^^''i^'^ 
n ,' 
.■«7^ 
&» 
•th:*: 
M^^'^'^ 
* *; 
On October 10, 2013, four vehicles of ex-Seleka 
fighters drove from Bossangoa to Ouham-Bac 
where an ex-Seleka base as well as local Muslim 
residents had been attacked and killed in early 
September. As they drove towards Ouham-Bac, 
the ex-Seleka fighters repeatedly fired at fleeing 
civilians along the road. In the village of Wikamo, 
ex-Seleka fighters shot dead fourvillage residents. 
looted the local hospital and school, and then 
proceeded to systematically burn the village. 
A total of 198 buildings, representing 71% of 
the village, were destroyed by fire based on an 
analysis of satellite imagery recorded on the 
morning of December4, 2013. Destroyed buildings 
visible in the image above are circled in red. 
DESTROYED BUILDINGS 
(left) Detailed view of destruction 
in Zéré: Typically, arson attacks 
burn away thatched rooftops 
leaving loadbearing walls intact. 
Damage Analysis: Human Rights Watch; 
Satellite Sensor: Pléiades-IA; 
Image Copyright: CNES 2013; 
Source: Astrium. 
34THEYCAMETO KILL 
THEYCAMETO KILL35 


V HUMANITARIAN CATASTROPHE: 
"LIVINGAND DYING LIKE ANIMALS" 
At least 40,000 people are living in make-shift shelters on the grounds ofthe Catholic church 
in Bossangoa. The human rights abuses committed by ex-Seleka forces and anti-balaka 
militias have caused massive displacement of civilians in the area. November 3, 2013. 
© 2013 Marcus Bleasdale/VII for Human Rights Watch 
THE DISPLACEMENT CRISIS 
The human rights abuses committed by ex-Seleka forces and anti- 
balaka militias in northern CentralAfrican Republic have resulted 
in massive destruction and displacement in the area, causing a 
humanitarian catastrophe. Some 450,000 people have been forced 
to fiee their homes because ofthe violence, including 170,000 in 
Ouham province alone.^* 
Ofthose displaced in Ouham province, some 40,000 Christians 
have sought refuge in extremely crowded conditions around 
the Catholic church in Bossangoa, while some 4,000 displaced 
Muslims are sheltering on the opposite side of Bossangoa at the 
Ecole Liberté and nearby government buildings. 
The displacement crisis is a direct result ofthe human rights 
abuses committed primarily by ex-Seleka fighters. Their modus 
operandi has been to attack villages by arriving at high speed 
in 4x4 vehicles, immediately begin shooting at the fieeing 
population, and then setting entire villages on fire. Most villages 
in the Central African Republic are very close to the main roads, 
makingthemveryvulnerabletosuch surprise attacks, atactic 
previously used bythe Presidential Guard of then-president Bozizé 
during counterinsurgency operations.^^ 
The ex-Seleka's arson attacks have resulted in the burning of 
countless villages and towns across northern Central African 
Republic, particularly in Ouham and Ouham-Pendé provinces. 
Using site visits and satellite imagery analysis. Human Rights 
Watch has documented arson attacks on vast stretches of villages 
overthe entire confiict-affected region, demonstrating both their 
systematic and widespread nature.^^ 
ofthe attack. 
86 According to the UN estimates, 394,979 persons were internally displaced 
because ofthe conflict as of September 30, 2013, and another 64,717 new 
refugees from CentralAfrican Republic had fled to neighboring countries. See 
UN Office forthe Coordination of Humanitarian Affairs (OCHA), CentralAfrican 
Republic: Situation Report No. 30 (as of 8 November 2013, available at https:// 
car.humanitarianresponse.info/fr/system/files/documents/files/Situation%20 
Report%2030_EN.pdf. 
87 See Human Rights Watch, CentralAfrican Republic-State of Anarchy 
Rebellion and Abuses against Civilians, September 2007, http://www.hrw.org/ 
reports/2007/09/14/state-anarchy. 
88 Josh Lyons, "What a War Crime Looks Like From Space" Human Rights Watch 
dispatch, November 26, 2013, http://www.hrw.org/news/2013/ll/26/dispatches- 
V" ■   '-'^A' 
# 
i 
Xs 
~^( 
r-7 -r '    rV 
• 

t.      m 
f 
4 
w 
Wi 
36THEYCAMET0KILL 
THEYCAMETO KILL37 


BOSSANGOA 
(CAMP COORDINATES: 6.496N, 17.449E) 
Satellite Image Date: December 4, 2013 
Satellite Image Date: December 12, 2013 
I 
y 
> 
W( 
f 
% 
m 
^ 
Â. 
S. 
*^ 
r 
!==r 
« 
i 
/ 
1 
f, 
^ 
füi. 
rw 
c^ 
w 
^ 
Ji 
1% 
> 
» 
I- 
'^ 
ê^ 
r.'ip^H 
~r- 
« 
« 
% 
« 
^j 
Ä 
4M 
"H 
4 
b^ 
%. 
y 
Since July 2013, several hundred displaced Muslim civilians sought shelter within the main buildings of 
a local school (Ecole Liberté) in the Muslim Boro quarter of Bossangoa. A large-scale attack by Christian 
anti-balaka fighters in Bossangoa on December 5, 2013 left 11 residents dead and multiple buildings 
destroyed. The number of displaced in Boro dramatically increased when over 7,000 local Muslims 
residents sought emergency shelter and protection at the school which was heavily protected by African 
Union troops and the ex-Seleka fighters at the time. 
Satellite imagery recorded on the mornings of December 4 and 12, 2013, captures the rapid expansion 
ofthe Ecole Liberté camp forover 7,000 displaced Muslims civilians in the Boro quarter of Bossangoa. 
Damage Analysis: Human Rights Watch; 
Satellite Sensor: Pléiades-lA; 
Image Copyright: CNES 2013; 
Source: Astrium. 
38THEYCAMET0KILL 
THEYCAMETO KILL39 
 

THE HEALTH CRISIS 
Tens ofthousands of displaced people have sought 
shelter in larger population centers, such as 
Bossangoa, where there are some very basic medical 
facilities in place, as well as sanitary measures and 
safe water supplies aimed at preventing the outbreak 
of communicable diseases. Even in these larger 
population centers, however, many medical needs are 
unmet. For example. Human Rights Watch documented 
cases in Bossangoa's main camp for internally 
displaced persons at the Catholic church where teenage 
girls gave birth unassisted, endangering their lives and 
those oftheir babies. 
An even more severe health crisis is unfolding outside 
the main population centers in the CentralAfrican 
Republic, in the rural countryside where tens of 
thousands have fied their burned-out or abandoned 
villages and are living in rudimentary shelters, often 
close to their rural fields. Many of these villagers live 
too far away from the main population centers to 
relocate there, feel unsafe passing through Seleka 
checkpoints, or prefer to remain close to their fields 
where food is available. 
Human Rights Watch found that in September, 
Bossangoa-based ex-Seleka forces had systematically 
looted and destroyed the vitally important medical 
centers and pharmacies in secondary population centers 
around Bossangoa, particularly in Ndjo, Ouham-Bac, and 
Zéré. These medical centers and pharmacies, located in 
major trading centers, serve the surrounding villages, so 
their looting affects health care in the entire area. 
Human Rights Watch also met with a nurse from the Ndjo 
medical center, 32, who had just lost his sister Delphine 
Yamini, 37, to malaria. He showed Human Rights Watch 
his medical case—it contained a single bandage, and 
some medical tools he had managed to save from the 
destroyed clinic. He told Human Rights Watch: 
My sister died just 48 hours ago. She had a bad 
case of malaria, and anemia. There was nothing 
I could do. We live and die like animals here. The 
effectiveness ofa nurse like me depends on our 
access to medications.... The biggest problem is 
malaria. We have five or six deaths a week in the 
area. A mother came to me sick with malaria just a 
few minutes before you arrived, and I had to send 
her away... 
All of these people dying in the bush because of 
health problems, it started after the Seleka looted 
the clinic and the pharmacy on September 16. They 
came in four vehicles. We heard their gunshots 
and fled into the bush. On the 17'^ we went with 
the village chief to look at the damage. We found 
one boy, Silas Dewan, 14, shot dead from bullets. 
We found nothing left at our clinic. They took 
everything—they took even the mattresses, but the 
biggest loss for us was the medications they looted. 
Before that day, I had enough medicines to treat the 
people.''" 
l^W^- 
% 
M 
i '.^   . 
. -l».»:! . 
/^ 
^-. 
J. 
'% 
% 
:■ » 
■in 
i-'J^jti... ., 
N 
^. 
^-.'^»CJ^^ 
i 
y% 
* 
■s 
M 
é 
*-*h*ä^j=* 
s_ 
iï- 
toHMMÜi 
Raphaël Newane, a village chief from Ndjo, stands in front ofthe graves of 
his two grandchildren, who died from malaria a week before this photo was 
taken. Novembers, 2013 
© 2013 Marcus Bleasdale/VII for Human Rights Watch 
In the abandoned market and gold-mining town of 
Ndjo, Human Rights Watch asked some displaced 
people to take its research team to their shelters in the 
bush. The team had to walk for about four kilometers, 
crossing a river, to reach the area where about 
14,000 displaced persons had sought shelter in small 
improvised shelters. The first person encountered was 
Raphaël Newane, 55, a village chief from Ndjo, who 
showed Human Rights Watch the graves of his two 
grandchildren who, he said, had died from malaria just 
one week earlier: Fredianne Mobene, 9 months, and 
Aurélie Newane, 6 months.^' 
what-war-crime-looks-space. 
89 Human Rights Watch interview with Rafel Newane, Ndjo, November 
5,2013. 
90 Human Rights Watch interviewwith a resident of Ndjo, Ndjo, Novem- 
bers, 2013. 
40THEYCAMETO KILL 
THEYCAMETO KILL41 


THE EDUCATION CRISIS 
On most ofthe blackboards in the abandoned schools visited 
by Human Rights Watch in October 2013 around Bossangoa, the 
date ofthe last lesson is almost invariably in March—the month 
Seleka took power in Bangui. Since March 2013, almost the entire 
school-age population in this region has been out of school. 
Nationally, more than 70 percent of school-age children—at least 
450,000 children—are currently out of school, an education 
crisis of immense proportions.^'^ Even in large population centers 
like Bossangoa, Human Rights Watch found that schools are not 
operafing, and are often occupied by displaced persons in need 
of shelter. The Ecole Liberté in Bossangoa, for example, currently 
houses some 4,000 displaced Muslims in its classrooms. 
While many schools are closed because the villages in which 
they are situated have been burned or abandoned as a result 
ofthe fighting, the schools visited by Human Rights Watch in 
Ndjo, Zéré, and Ouham-Bac had been systematically looted of 
their books and other essential supplies by ex-Seleka fighters. A 
September 2013 inter-agency assessment of schools in Central 
African Republic found that nationwide, 64 percent of all schools 
had been extensively looted (by both armed groups and civilians), 
a figure that rose to more than 90 percent in two ofthe provinces 
assessed.^'^ Among the items commonly found looted or destroyed 
are the metal roofs ofthe schools, textbooks, desks, canteen 
equipment, and the schools' official records.^'^ 
A school in Bossangoa that was operating until March 2013, when the Seleka took 
power in Bangui. Almost the entire school-age population in this region has been 
out of school since March. The school is now used as a shelterfor people displaced 
bythe fighting between ex-Seleka and anti-balaka forces. November3, 2013. 
© 2013 Marcus Bleasdale/VII for Human Rights Watch 
91  Fora detailed assessment, see UN Interagency Education Cluster, "A Step Back: 
The Impact ofthe Recent Crisis on Education in the CentralAfrican Republic," Sep- 
tember 2013, available at https://car.humanitarianresponse.info/fr/system/files/ 
documents/files/EC%20CAR%20-%20lmpact%20crisis%20on%20education%20 
-%20Evaluation%20Report%20EN.pdf. The assessment was done before renewed 
fighting broke out in Ouham, Ouham-Pendé, and other provinces, so the actual 
numberof students outof school at the moment is probably even higher than the 
70 percent estimated in the assessment report. 
92 "A step Back," p. 20. 
93  Ibid. 
^ 
/ 
lOT 
f.-^ 
m 
ir^ ^. 1 
-4s 
J 
» 
<i 
^ 
ra 
/ 
m 
¥• 
lkiiA,iM>«mVO/; 
ü^ii 
'■^akvj" 
P- 
W 
i 
42THEYCAMET0KILL 
THEYCAMETO KILL43 


^ 
V 
-r 
>t 
^ ' 
!>. 
5{ 
■». 
1 
»■ 
K. 
< 
^»^* 
i 
^ 
:» 
*t 
»> 
i< 
hfe 
'Ai 
.*r 
^, 
^ 
^ 
af, 
v\ 
/ 
^ 
^ 

"r--* 
•i 
\ 
S/ 


t 
^ 
rlHÊROU 
> 
^    i 
«M 
> 
« 
/ 
é 
<. 
ym- 
k 
r» 
j^j. 
'\ 
# 
^ 
/ 
^\ 
% 
X 
I 
\ 
^% 
::! 
^ 
▼•n 
i»^ 
^ 
% 
^ 
>• 
Anti-balaka fighters have recruited and.armed children in villages 
gy                             surrounding Bossangoa. November 3, 2013. 
® 2013 Marcus Bleasdale/VII for Human Rights Watch 
.iiVA..tA .       1.^ î-i.;'i, ;    '%i^"^-f".,^i».-.w-i... 

 
